- [Instructor] We have seen with multiple examples
how to manage the states
with the React API with useState, with useReducer
and also useContext.
With useState, you can create local state variables
that remain attached to one component only.
And with useReducer, you can manage complex logic separate
from one component.
And useContext allows to create and share global state
without having to pass data down manually
from top to bottom with one single source of truth.
So every hook has its own benefits.
The React API has certain limitations though.
For example, component state can only be shared
by pushing it up to the common ancestor.
And that is the same challenge as with props really,
meaning that the state is kept
in one location to pass data down from top to bottom,
which is not very flexible.
And with context, you can only store one single value.
These limitations make it difficult to split the code
from the tree where the state leaves
from the leaves of the tree.
By leaves, I mean the components
where the state is consumed.
To go beyond the limitations of the React API,
new solutions like Recoil comes in very handy.
Recoil acts like React
with a seamless syntax, semantic and behavior
but with more capabilities and Recoil has the same simple
and minimal interface as with React with the get and sets.
So let me explain to you how it works.
Recoil is using atomic approach,
meaning that developers can define atoms
that represents pieces of data.
And so the atoms
are like independent objects containing the data.
Then the data is shared down into React components
through selectors, which are pure functions.
The library also provide with hooks
that makes it easy to access
and update the state from within React components.
So let's begin with a new example.
In the next example, we are building a to-do list.
The features are very simple.
We're going to have a list of items
and we have also the options to add new items
with options also to filter the list.
So we also enable the feature to cross items off the list
so to indicate that this is completed.
Then you can also delete the items that are completed
and decide to only filter
and display the items that are completed.
So this is a very basic example built with the React API.
Here the challenge is the same.
If you ever need to scale the app, you need an efficient way
to share data between components without making components
depending on each other.
So the first step is to make the application aware
of the state with RecoilRoot.
RecoilRoot is an important component
of the Recoil library.
It is a component that provides the context
in which atoms have values, and it must be apparent
of any component that uses any Recoil hook.
I will show you how.
First we want to make sure that we install the Recoil library.
Then we go into our projects.
Right here.
We're going to make sure that first we install Recoil.
So it looks like this is not possible to actually paste.
So I'm going to do npm i and recoil.
And next, while this is being installed,
I'm just going to grab, so let's go back to RecoilRoot.
And the way it should be is that you're going to add
to the scope of your entry point in your React project
and make sure that you wrap the app components.
So the root component with the RecoilRoot component.
Okay, so this is done.
So let's go find the index.js,
add this to the scope like this
and we're going to wrap the root component with RecoilRoot.
That's going to be the first step
in order to make any descending component aware
of the context.
And so any descending component can access
and update the state
by accessing the state through the RecoilRoot.
So in a nutshell,
Recoil is a tool that helps developers manage the state
in their React applications, making it easier
to build complex and robust user interfaces.
Coming next, we're going to see
how to divide the state management by using atoms.
So we're going to see how to create atoms
that are independent objects containing the state
of your app.